<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Lab resources | Steen Lab</title>
    <link>https://adsteen.github.io/lab-resources/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://adsteen.github.io/lab-resources/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Lab resources</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020</copyright>
    <image>
      <url>https://adsteen.github.io/img/lab_logo.png</url>
      <title>Lab resources</title>
      <link>https://adsteen.github.io/lab-resources/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>marie quickstart</title>
      <link>https://adsteen.github.io/lab-resources/marie/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2020 12:29:43 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://adsteen.github.io/lab-resources/marie/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The SteenLab server is named marie for Marie Tharp, a pioneering oceanographer who used sounding data collected by others to create the first high-quality bathymetric map of the world&amp;rsquo;s oceans. In that spirit, we hope that you will use marie to gain a new understanding of how the planet and the microbial world work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;getting-an-account&#34;&gt;Getting an account&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To access marie, you will need the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A University of Tennessee email account.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An account on marie. If you don&amp;rsquo;t have one already, ask permission from Drew Steen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A virtual private network (VPN) client, such as PulseSecure, connected to University of Tennessee&amp;rsquo;s VPN.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A shell on your computer.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are using a Mac, it is easiest to use the Bash or zsh shells that come default with OS X. This is what you get when you open the &amp;lsquo;Terminal&amp;rsquo; program.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are using a PC, it is a little more complicated. In newer versions of Windows 10, you can enable a true, Linux-based Bash shell by enabling Windows Subsystem for Linux. If that isn&amp;rsquo;t possible, the best alternative is probably to use Git Bash. It is also possible to use the Windows-native PowerShell, but this will require you to learn two different shell languages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A very basic understanding of how to use a Linux shell such as Bash, and a basic idea of how to use conda environments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;getting-started&#34;&gt;Getting started&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take the following steps to access marie:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure that you are connected to UT&amp;rsquo;s VPN. If you are using PulseSecure, there will be a little green arrow on the PulseSecure logo when you are connected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open your shell (Terminal on OS X, Git Bash or similar on Windows).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Type &lt;code&gt;ssh &amp;lt;username&amp;gt;@marie.bio.utk.edu&lt;/code&gt;, replacing &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; with your username, and enter your password when prompted. You will now be connected to marie, so that any commands you type into your shell are executed on marie.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Activate a conda environment. &lt;em&gt;Note to self: I&amp;rsquo;d like to edit everyone&amp;rsquo;s .bashrc so that it will automatically start a lab-default conda environment on login.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Congratulations! You can now run jobs on marie to your heart&amp;rsquo;s content.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;rules&#34;&gt;Rules&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:troyalty@vols.utk.edu&#34;&gt;Taylor Royalty&lt;/a&gt; is marie&amp;rsquo;s system administrator. What he says, goes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;passwords-and-security&#34;&gt;Passwords and security&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;marie is subject to frequent hacking attempts. We have already had to wipe the system clean once due to a successful takeover by hackers. Thus, please take these rules seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you are given a marie account, your password will be set to a random 8-character string. I urge you to keep your password in a password manager such as LastPass, rather than an unencrypted file such as a Word document or similar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You may change your password, but if you do, change it to another randomly-generated 8-or-more character string, for example one generated by a password manager. Please do not use a password containing real words, birthdays, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We will inform you of your password in person or via text message or similar. Please do not write your password in an email.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All of this is on the honor system. However, violation of password rules is grounds for having your marie account revoked.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;use-of-conda-environments&#34;&gt;Use of conda environments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use a conda environment for all of your work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you think you need to install software outside of a conda environment, check with Taylor or Drew first.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hard-drive-use&#34;&gt;Hard drive use&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right now, hard drive space is not a problem. In the future we may implement limits on hard drive use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Common data sets, such as the SwissProt database, are stored at &lt;em&gt;TBD&lt;/em&gt;. All users may read but not write to that space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Users must keep their own data in their own directory, &lt;code&gt;~/&amp;lt;username&amp;gt;/&lt;/code&gt;. If you download data that you think would be useful to others, please contact Taylor or Drew to put it in &lt;em&gt;the public data directory TBD&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;marie&amp;rsquo;s hard drives are under RAID control, which give some resilience to hard drive failure. However, each user is responsible for backing up essential data, code and results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Users are urged to organize their directories logically, with one folder for each project. Within each project directory, data should be kept in the &lt;code&gt;data&lt;/code&gt; directory, code in dedicated directories, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Users are strongly encouraged to keep their code under git control, so that it is easier to recover from mistakes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
